Guide to the John F. Hogan Papers, 1928-1992 and undated, bulk 1949-1972 RL.00558
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
John F. Hogan papers
1928-1992 and undated bulk 1949-1972
bulk
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Hogan, John F.
RL.00558
10 Linear Feet
John F. Hogan was a sales representative and manager for several transportation advertising companies, from the 1940s to the 1970s, responsible for placing advertisements in and on buses, subways, trains, and transit stations in the northeastern United States, particularly New York and Connecticut. The John F. Hogan Papers span the years 1928-1992, with the bulk of the material dating from 1949 to 1972, and document Hogan's career as an executive in transportation advertising. The collection consists of photographs, contracts, poster samples, print publications and other printed material, and scrapbooks of transit advertising images, clippings, correspondence and memorabilia. Particularly represented in the collection is Hogan's work for the John H. Breck, Inc. hair-care company.
7,250 Items
Access Restrictions
Collection is restricted.
Scrapbook originals are closed to researchers. Use copies are available in the collection.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. There may be a 48-hour delay in obtaining these materials.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The John F. Hogan Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 1995.
Biographical Note
Chronology
1910 June 21 Born in Manhattan, N.Y.
1928 Graduated Oakwood (Preparatory) School, Poughkeepsie, N.Y.
1928-1936 Held positions of office boy, clerk, charge of Records and Research, Assistant to Sales Manager, with the Collier Service Corporation (New York)
1936 Graduated Fordham College, B.S. cum laude (night classes)
1936-1938 Sales Representative, Collier Service Corporation
1938-1941 Territorial salesman, H.J. Heinz Co., N.Y.
1941 Sales Representative, Car Cards Inc., N. Y.
1941-1942 Sales Representative, Surface Transportation Advertising, Inc., N.Y.
1942 July 11 Married Ruth Irene Bertsehy (Divorced 1980)
1942-1946 Army of the United States (A.U.S.)--Signal Corps Officer Candidate School, Ft. Monmouth, N. J. Promoted to 2nd Lt. 1943 Apr. 9. Served in the U.S. and Philippines. Discharged as Captain in 1946
1946-1948 Sales Representative, Surface Transportation Advertising, Inc., N.Y.
1949-1951 Exclusive Local Sales Manager, L.I.R.R. (Long Island Rail Road) Transit Advertisers, Inc.
1951-1953 Sales Representative, Manager--Connecticut Territory, Transit Advertisers, Inc.
1953-1955 Sales Representative, Manager Connecticut Territory, Philbin & Coine, N.Y.
1951-1955 Member, Advertising Club of Hartford, Conn.
1956-1957 Sales Representative, Hudson Tubes Advertising Corp.
1958 Account Executive, Savings and Loan Publications, Columbus, Ohio
1959-1972 Sales Representative, National Sales Manager, Philbin & Coine, N.Y.
1973-1975 Account Executive, Communications Channels Inc. Publications, N.Y.
1976 Sales Representative, Transportation Displays Inc., N.Y.
1977 Jan.-Apr. Sales Representative, Philbin & Coine, N.Y.
1977 May-Aug. Account Executive, Douglas Leigh Transit Advertising, N.Y.
Throughout his career, Hogan represented local advertising agencies such as Cronin Avertising, Bergin and Nolan, etc. He also sold printing, an essential component of transit advertising.
Collection Overview
The John F. Hogan Papers span the years 1928-1992, with the bulk of the material dating from 1949 to 1972, and consist of photographs, contracts, printed materials, scrapbooks and images of transit station posters and car cards that document Hogan's career placing advertising within the bus, subway and rail systems in the northeastern United States, particularly in New York and Connecticut. Several agencies and client companies are represented in the collection, including the John H. Breck, Inc. hair-care company.
The Papers are organized into six series: Scrapbooks, Contracts, Printed Materials, John H. Breck Inc., Electric Bus Clocks and Photographs. The Scrapbooks Series contains scrapbooks, compiled by Hogan in 1992, which include correspondence, clippings, printed material, photographs, and narrative written by Hogan. The Contracts Series contains contracts for the placement of transportation advertising in the northeastern United States, primarily in New York and Connecticut. The Printed Materials Series includes books, booklets, magazines, house organs and trade journals related to the subject of transportation advertising, along with non-titled print items such as rate cards, articles, clippings, and promotional materials. The John H. Breck Inc. Series includes correspondence, printed materials, clippings, and contracts relating to transportation advertising for Breck hair care products, such as Breck shampoo. The Electric Bus Clocks Series includes correspondence, printed materials, and clippings related to transportation advertisements which featured electric clocks. Examples of the car card advertisements, posters and signs can be found in the Photographs Series,which includes many undated black and white car card reproductions, along with color photographs of exterior bus signs taken in Connecticut during the 1950s and 1960s.
Related Archival Materials note
Related materials may be found in the Bates Worldwide Inc. Records and the Outdoor Advertising Association of America Archives.
Car cards; Posters; Photographs; Scrapbooks; Clocks and watches, electric; Transportation; Hair preparations; Advertising executives; Advertising agencies -- United States; Advertising -- Toilet preparations; Advertising -- Transportation -- Connecticut; Advertising -- Transportation -- New York; Advertising -- Transportation; Advertising, Outdoor; John H. Breck, Inc.; John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History; Hogan, John F.; Hogan, John F.
- Scrapbooks Series, 1928-1992, 2 boxes
  Scope and Contents note
  Contains scrapbooks, compiled by Hogan in 1992, that include correspondence, clippings, printed material, photographs, and narratives written by Hogan. They are in roughly chronological order and follow Hogan's career in transportation advertising.
  Conditions Governing Access note
  Original scrapbooks are closed to researchers. Please consult the use copies located in Box 2.
  - Original Scrap Books (Closed to researchers: see use copies) (Box 1)
    - Volume 1, 1928-1992 (Box 1)
    - Volume 2, 1937-1955 (Box 1)
    - Volume 3, 1953-1957 (Box 1)
    - Volume 4, 1941, 1959-1977 (Box 1)
  - Use Copies of Scrapbooks (Box 2)
    - Volume 1, 1928-1992 (Box 2)
    - Volume 2, 1937-1955 (Box 2)
    - Volume 3, 1953-1957 (Box 2)
    - Volume 4, 1941, 1959-1977 (Box 2)
- Contracts Series, 1938-1975 and undated, 2 boxes
  Contains contracts for the placement of transportation advertising in the northeastern United States, mostly New York and Connecticut. Some clippings and correspondence are attached to a few contracts. Photographs exist for some contracts. See cross-reference sheets for the location of photographs removed from contracts and placed in the Photographs Series. A few magazine advertisement proofs exist with contracts for California Prunes. In addition to the contracts executed by Hogan, the series also contains contracts executed by J.L. Tribble for Transit Advertisers Inc. prior to Hogan's employment with that company. Hogan used a variety of systems for the arrangement of contracts: chronological, location, and client/product category. Arranged alphabetically.
  - Hudson Tubes Advertising Corp. (Box 2)
    - General, 1955-1957 (Box 2)
    - Clients
      - California Prunes, 1956-1957 (Box 2)
      - R.J. Reynolds, 1956-1957 (Box 2)
    - Correspondence relating to contracts, 1956-1957 (Box 2)
  - Surface Transportation Advertising, Inc.
    - Sales records, 1946-1949 (Box 2)
  - Transit Advertisers Inc.
    Name changed to Philbin & Coine in 1953.
    - J.L. Tribble files, 1938, 1940-1951, 12 folders (Box 2)
    - Locations
      - Connecticut, 1951-1955, 5 folders (Box 2)
      - New York, 1949-1951, 3 folders (Box 2)
      - Station clocks, New Haven Railroad, 1949-1950 (Box 2)
    - Philbin & Coine
      - Blank contracts, undated (Box 2)
      - Chronological file, 1953-1955, 2 folders (Box 2)
      - Clients
        - Communication Channels Inc., 1973-1975 (Box 2)
        - Connecticut Milk, 1952-1970 (Box 2)
        - Grocery products, 1959-1972 (Box 2)
          Includes Almar Packing, Bertoli Olive Oil, Progresso Foods, Pure Maid Orange Juice, PJ Ritter Foods, Vita Food Products, Coca Cola, Dr. Pepper, Bon Core Wine.
        - Hull Brewing, 1951-1972 (Box 2)
        - National Distillers, 1968-1972 (Box 2)
        - Pepsi-Cola, 1952-1972 (Box 2)
        - Political, 1952-1972, 2 folders (Box 3)
        - Roessler Packing, 1957-1972 (Box 3)
        - Scotches, 1960-1970 (Box 3)
          Includes Schenley, Cutty Sark, Clan MacGregor, Cluny, Black Bull.
        - Seven-Up, 1959-1972 (Box 3)
        - Southern Connecticut Gas Co., 1959-1972 (Box 3)
        - Tassette, controversial, 1959-1960 (Box 3)
        - Torrington's mini bus, 1962, 1968 (Box 3)
        - Various multi-city advertising, 1958-1972 (Box 3)
          Includes American Driving School, Capital Cities Broadcasting (WTNH-TV Channel 8), City Trust Co., Connecticut Commercial Travelers, Connecticut National Bank, New Haven Business School, Putnam House Restaurant, Roto-Rooter Service, Southern New England Telephone, Speedwriting, State National Bank, WPLR-FM Radio.
      - Locations (Conn.)
        - Bridgeport, 1958-1972 (Box 3)
        - Danbury, Derby, Norwalk, New Britain, Springfield, 1958-1970 (Box 3)
        - New Haven, 1947-1972 (Box 3)
        - Stamford, 1958-1972 (Box 3)
        - Waterbury, Torrington, 1959-1972 (Box 3)
      - Rates and data, 1953-1976 (Box 3)
- Printed Materials Series, 1928-1977 and undated, 2 boxes
  Series is divided into two subseries: Publications; and Other Printed Materials. The Publications Subseries includes reports, manuals, trade journals and serial publications relating to the transit advertising industry. The Other Printed Materials Subseries includes clippings relating to labor disputes and strikes in the transit industry between 1955 and 1975 (Hudson Tubes, the Connecticut Railway and Lighting Co., and the Connecticut Company bus system). Also included are several car card advertisements for General Electric from the 1950s. Arranged alphabetically.
  Large format items have been removed to Oversize Materials. A note so indicating has been inserted in the finding aid at the item's original location. Where an entire folder has been so removed, the folder title will appear in brackets to indicate its logical location within the finding aid.
  - Publications Subseries, 1928-1977 and undated
    - $6 3/4 Billion Market and How You Can Sell It, 1950s (Box 3)
      Publication of Hudson Tubes.
    - Andy Awards '67, 1968 (Box 3)
    - BMT Advertiser, 1934 July-1935 Jan. (Box 3)
      Publication of Brooklyn Manhattan Transit; continued by the CSC Advertiser.
    - Canadian Media, Standard Rates and Data Service, 1953 Aug. 5 (Box 3)
    - CSC Advertiser, 1935 May-1937 Jan. (Box 3)
      Publication of Collier Service Corporation; continues BMT Advertiser.
    - Daily Except Sundays, 1938 (Box 3)
      Produced by Edward Streeter and illustrated by Gluyas Williams; published for Transit Advertisers Inc.
    - Fame: A Journal for Advertisers, 1935 Feb.-1937 Dec. (Box 3)
      House organ for the Interborough Rapid Transit.
    - In N.Y. City, This is Outdoor Advertising, ca. 1977 (Box 3)
      Published by Douglas Leigh Transit Advertising.
    - Interborough Rapid Transit Sales Manual, 1928 (Box 3)
    - The King Size Millions (Chicago), ca. 1965 (Box 3)
    - Lexicon of Terms Commonly Used in Transit Advertising, 1969 (Box 3)
    - National Association of Transportation Advertising (NATA), 1949-1951 (Box 3)
    - National Real Estate Investor, 1973 Sept. (Box 3)
      Published by Communication Channels Inc.
    - N.Y. Subway Advertising Circulation Analysis, 1947, 1953 (Box 3)
    - Plants, Sites, & Parks, 1974 Mar./Apr. (Box 3)
    - Producing Low-Cost Results with Transportation Advertising, undated (Box 3)
    - Reading and Riding and 'rithmetic, 1946 (Box 3)
    - Shopping Center World, 1974 May (Box 3)
    - Some Questions and Answers About Advertising, ca. 1955 (Box 3)
      By Elon G. Borton.
    - Standard Rates and Data Service, Transportation Advertising, 1952 Feb.-1977 May (Incomplete run) (Box 4)
    - Study of Outside Transit Poster Exposure, 1959 (Box 5)
    - Successful Business, 1955 Sept.-1969 May (Not a complete run) (Box 5)
    - Suggestions for the Advancement of Outdoor Advertising, 1962 (Box 5)
      Publication of American Association of Advertising Agencies (AAAA).
    - Tide, 1950 May 19 (Box 5)
      Cover story on transportation advertising.
    - Transit Advertising, 1970 (Box 5)
      By George T. Clarke; published by the Transit Advertising Association.
    - Transit Advertising and the Bus of Tomorrow, 1963 (Box 5)
      Publication of American Transit Association.
    - Transit Millions: Under-Million Markets Edition, 1964 (Box 5)
    - Transit Record, 1958 (Box 5)
      Publication of N.Y. City Transit Authority.
    - Transportation Advertising, 1940-1948, 1950 (Box 5)
      By James Benton Lackey; published by Harvard Business School.
    - U.S. Transit Advertising $ Volume, 1966 (Box 5)
  - Other Printed Material Subseries, 1920s-1977 and undated
    Includes non-titled printed materials, such as rate cards, articles, clippings, and promotional materials, along with maps of bus, subway, and rail lines, posters, and car card advertisements. Arranged alphabetically.
    - Articles relating to transportation advertising, 1938-1968 (Box 5)
    - Bendix washers and Bulova watches, 1949 (Box 5)
      Miscellaneous printed materials including car card reproductions.
    - Bus sign frames, 1949-1970 (Box 5)
      Materials relating to design and specifications. See Photographs Series for cross references.
    - Bus sign production specifications, 1952-1977 (Box 5)
      Includes paint, paper and board samples.
    - [Car card advertisements: removed to Oversize Materials] (Box 5)
    - Clippings, 1955-1975 (Box 5)
      Mainly relate to labor disputes and strikes on the Hudson Tubes, the Connecticut Railway and Lighting Co. and the Connecticut Co. bus system.
    - Connecticut Milk Producers Association, promotional materials, 1955-1964 (Box 5)
    - Frigidaire car card reproductions, 1949-1952 (Box 5)
      See Photographs Series for cross references.
    - General Electric car card reproduction booklets, 1950-1954 (Box 5)
    - [Maps: removed to Oversize Materials] (Box 5)
    - [Posters: removed to Oversize Materials] (Box 5)
    - Promotional materials, 1953-1957 and undated (Box 5)
      Includes materials for Alpo Dog Food, Handy's Brightwood Products, Old Taylor Bourbon, Progresso Foods, Calvert Whiskey, Pure Maid Orange Juice, California Prunes; see Photographs Series for cross references.
    - Rate cards, 1920s-1975
      - Bauer & Meyer Inc. (CR&L Lines), 1940s (Box 5)
      - Communication Channels Inc., 1973-1975 (Box 5)
        Includes Shopping Center World; National Real Estate Investor; Plants, Sites and Parks.
      - Douglas Leigh Transit Advertising Inc., undated (Box 5)
      - Hudson Tubes, 1920s or 1930s, 1956 (Box 5)
      - Mutual Transportation Advertising Inc., undated (Box 5)
      - Red Arrow Lines, 1953 (Box 5)
      - Surface Transportation Advertising, Inc., 1945-1947 (Box 5)
      - Transit Advertisers, Inc., 1941-1950 (Box 5)
      - Transportation Displays Inc. (TDI), 1976 (Box 5)
      - Worcester Street Railway Company, 1948-1951 (Box 5)
    - Receipts
      - Frank's Restaurant, Hartford, Conn., 1955 (Box 5)
    - Sales brochures
      - Transportation Displays, Inc. (TDI) 1975, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Oversize Materials
    - Car Card Advertisements (Oversize-folder 1)
      - American Gas Association (Oversize-folder 1)
      - General Electric (Oversize-folder 1)
      - Goodall, Palm Beach Slacks (Oversize-folder 1)
      - Highpoint (Oversize-folder 1)
      - John H. Breck Inc. (Oversize-folder 1)
      - Lewyt Vacuum Cleaners (Oversize-folder 1)
      - Speedwriting School (Oversize-folder 1)
      - Trans American Airlines (Oversize-folder 1)
      - Winston Cigarettes (Oversize-folder 1)
    - Maps, 1936-1975 (Oversize-folder 1)
    - Posters, undated
      - Antique Exposition and Sale (Oversize-folder 1)
      - Home Expo (Oversize-folder 1)
      - Madison Square Garden Antique Show (Oversize-folder 1)
      - Motor Boat Show (Oversize-folder 1)
      - N.Y. Coliseum (Oversize-folder 1)
- John H. Breck Inc. Series, 1944-1955, 1 box
  Correspondence, printed material, clippings and contracts relating to transportation advertising by John H. Breck Inc. See Oversize Materials within the Printed Materials Series for car card advertisements. See Photographs Series for cross references.
  - Breck Gold Box,, The Advertising Media We Use, 1955 (Box 5)
  - Dioramas, 1944-1953 (Box 5)
  - Mitchell, McCandless & Klaus (Cleveland), 1954-1955 (Box 5)
  - National coverage, 1951-1955 (Box 5)
- Electric Bus Clocks Series, 1955-1959, 1 box
  Correspondence, printed materials, and clippings, related to transportation advertisements which featured electric clocks. Included is a booklet written for the manufacturer of the clocks which includes a personal history of John Hogan and a proposal for electric clock advertisements on the N.Y. City Subway System. See Photograph Series for cross references.
  - General, 1955-1959 (Box 5)
- Photographs Series, 1941-1972 and undated, 1 box
  Photographs of transportation advertisements. Included are car card reproductions, which are undated black and white copies of car card advertisements arranged by product category. Also included are color photographs of exterior bus signs taken in Connecticut during the 1950s and 1960s. These are arranged in product categories and by location of sign on the bus. Negatives exist for these photos. A few black and white photographs exist featuring advertisements on the interior and exterior of buses and subways. Two sample booklets of bus signs compiled by Hogan include mostly color photographs, similar to the exterior bus sign photographs taken in Connecticut in the 1950s and 1960s. Also included in this series are photographs separated from other series. Cross reference sheets indicate the part of the collection from which the photos were removed.
  - Bus sign sample booklets (Box 6)
    - Connecticut, 1960s (Box 6)
    - Miscellaneous, 1960s (Box 6)
  - Car card reproduction print information, undated (Box 6)
  - Car card reproductions, black/white, undated
    - Appliances--Household
      - Household (Box 6)
      - RCA Victor (Box 6)
    - Automobiles (Box 6)
    - Bakeries/Bread (Box 6)
    - Dairies (Box 6)
    - Department stores (Box 6)
    - Drug stores (Box 6)
    - Fashions (Box 6)
    - Financial (Box 6)
    - Florists (Box 6)
    - Fuel (Box 6)
    - Furniture (Box 6)
    - Gifts (Box 6)
    - Hardware (Box 6)
    - Jewelers (Box 6)
    - Laundry/Cleaners (Box 6)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 6)
    - Morticians (Box 6)
    - Opticians (Box 6)
    - Photography (Box 6)
    - Press/Radio (Box 6)
    - Real estate (Box 6)
    - Restaurants (Box 6)
    - Telephone (Box 6)
    - Travel (Box 6)
    - Utilities (Box 6)
  - Connecticut bus photos, black/white, 1951-1956 (Box 6)
  - Exterior bus bigns, Connecticut, color, 1950s-1960s, 3 folders
    - Automobiles (new and used cars, dealers, mufflers, rental cars, tires) (Box 6)
    - Banks (commercial, savings) (Box 6)
    - Beer and whiskey (Box 6)
    - Bus front signs (Box 6)
    - Bus painted sides (Box 6)
    - Bus rear signs (Box 6)
    - Dairy and milk (Box 6)
    - Media ( N.Y. Times, radio, television stations) (Box 6)
    - National or regional advertisers (Box 6)
    - Negatives, 3 folders (Box 6)
    - Pet food (Alpo, Calo dog and cat food) (Box 6)
    - Political (Box 6)
    - Soft drinks (Coca Cola, Pepsi Cola, No-Cal, RC, Seven-Up) (Box 6)
    - Utilities (Bridgeport Gas; New Haven Gas) (Box 6)
  - Hudson Tubes Inc., 1950s (Box 6)
  - Interior bus photos, black/white, 1941-1942 (Box 6)
  - Photographs removed from other Series
    See cross reference sheets attached to photo for other items relating to the photographs.
    - Contracts
      - Philbin & Coine, 1954-1972 (Box 6)
      - Printed materials relating to bus sign frames (Box 6)
      - Transit advertisers, 1949-1952 (Box 6)
    - John H. Breck, Inc., 1954 (Box 6)
    - Printed materials, 1953-1962 and undated (Box 6)